So, yeah. Hi,
everyone. And thanks
for coming to
Manchester Node.js
user group today. I'm
kidding, of course.
Thanks to Adam and
Thomas doing most of
the organizing
because I've
been away for a
while, so let's give
them a clap. And, of
course, thanks to
you guys
because it was a
really nice day
outside, but you all
nerds decided to
come here anyway,
so here we are. So,
yeah. I wanted to
talk about building
an AI-based CLI tool
in 2024.
The AI bit there is
mainly for the hype,
but I wanted to talk
about building a CLI
tool
in 2024. The problem
I saw while trying
to build a CLI tool
this year was that
there
aren't really --
there aren't that
many good articles
online about
building CLI tools.
Most of them are
from several eons
ago when it was like
Node.js 0.4 or
something, I guess.
So I decided to
create a talk around
this and also try to
create content
around this
so we can try to
understand how we
can build cross-compatible
OS, like cross-OS
compatible
CLIs using Node.js
now, and it's really
great at that. So,
yeah. I am the
writing.dev on
the Internet or the
writing.dev in most
places, including
Twitter. So, yeah.
Why? So why did
I want to build this?
Well, firstly, I was
experimenting with
AI just when the GPT
API
came out, so, yeah,
this is just a GPT
wrapper, in essence.
But, yeah, I think
it's really
cool to build
products around
elements nowadays
because of generative
AIs and stuff. You
can
build products which
are -- which can do
more -- I mean, it
sort of leads to non-deterministic
computing in a way.
And secondly, there's
more than one way of
building interfaces.
So this is Ryan
Hoover, the creator
of Product Hunt, who
commented on one of
the products
there saying that he's
interested in voice-driven
experiences, and,
yeah. So you see a
lot of
hype around that. So
just by
incorporating a
different kind of
interface into your
product,
you start generating
sort of ideas and
interest around your
product. And this
was a post or
a tweet by a VC, so
take it with a grain
of salt across, of
course, who said
that UI engineers
will lose their jobs
now because you can
just ask Siri to do
something, and then
it hooks
up into your app
using an API to
directly execute the
task. So, of course,
I wanted to
sort of go at the
back end of building
applications and try
to build something
which is just CLI-driven
for the start. So
what is the thing? I'll
give a quick demo of
how it works. And,
yeah,
parts of this --
yeah, just a content
warning. Some of the
slides that I'm
showing are light-themed.
I'm using a light-themed
with my co-editor,
so please don't
complain. And, yeah,
so how
does it work? So,
yeah, originally it
was called How, but
I changed the name
to Howitzer because
if you search for
How CLI Copilot, it
would just show
GitHub's copilot
instead. And, yeah,
so you can basically
ask questions to it
in natural language.
So you can ask
something
like how do I get my
system specs? And it
will then call the GPT
API, of course, and
it will give you the
command. Then you
can choose to run
the command which
then gives
you the output there
directly. So instead
of having to memorize
all of these
different
Unix commands, you
can just ask the CLI
tool directly.
Another simple thing
you might want
to do is, like, how
do I get the DNS
info of the writing.dev?
So I've already
completed
this already. So if
I run that, then,
yeah, it says dig
the writing.dev. If
I choose to
run this command,
then it gives the
output of the
command directly. So,
of course, as
you can see, it's a
very simple app.
Originally it was
less than 100 lines
of code, but then
I added some nice UX
around it which
increased the size a
little bit. But I'll
try to simplify
it as much as I can.
So, yeah, that is
the actual tool. And
now I want to go a
little
bit about the
problems and
solutions. So how
did I end up at this
phase? Of course. As
you can see, it's
just a simple
command. I say how
and then it
automatically runs
it
in the backend. So
it's a proper CLI
tool. But doing this
in Node.js is a
little bit
tough. So the first
problem is that, oh,
I think it's on a
timer probably, but,
yeah,
so the first problem
is that that I faced
was that TypeScript
sucks. I didn't want
to
write build tooling
around TypeScript.
So, for example, how
many ways are there
to build
a new TypeScript
project? I mean,
apart from one,
there's several,
like, for example,
TS
node, there's wheat,
there's parcel. I
mean, there's n
number of ways you
can build a TypeScript
project. But there's
one thing common
with all of them.
You're adding a
build step. So
you're adding
complexity into your
whole project. So
instead of that, I
wanted the ability
to
have types, but I
didn't want to have
a build step. So
what I did was use
ES modules instead.
If it's good enough
for Swelt, it's good
enough for your
project. So please
move to your ES
modules instead of
TypeScript to help
improve the
developer experience
around it.
ES modules have been
supported in Node.js
since 2019, actually,
and I'm going to
give
a demo of how they
actually look like.
So don't be afraid
of pushing,
publishing a library
to NPM, which is
just ES modules only.
And, yeah, basically
to start a -- I mean,
we saw
what it took to
start out with a
TypeScript project,
but for ES modules,
since it's Node
native, you can just
run NPM in it. Why,
of course.
Now to give you a
quick demo of what
the application --
the first version of
the application
actually
looks like. So
basically, I mean, I'm
using the OpenAI SDK,
of course. It's
actually really
good. It's an auto-generated
SDK based on their
APIs, so it's mostly
up-to-date. But
they haven't added GPT
4.0 mini to it yet
on the Type side. So
it's also sometimes
behind
unless they actually
run the SDK
generation process.
So yeah, a quick
explanation of what's
actually happening
here. It's actually
quite
straightforward.
I'm initializing a
new client based on
the OpenAI library.
In this case, it's
just picking
up the API key from
my environment
variables instead of
explicitly passing
it in. I'm
generating
a list of messages
here to pass to the
LLM. So a role in a
message is basically,
like,
what context is that
message being sent
in? Is it the user?
Is it the chatbot?
Or is it
like a system prompt?
Basically, you're
telling the LLM what
you want to do. So
in this case,
this is a prompt
that I built using
another LLM, of
course, because,
yeah, LLMs are
notoriously
difficult to give
the right prompts to.
So this basically
gives the users
command line
to the LLM. It gives
a negative prompt
saying that ignore
any pleasantries or
comments,
stuff like that. And
then it also gives
the user's operating
system to it. So it
tries
to make it as
operating system
independent as
possible. And we are
going to go towards
that.
And next, I'm
passing in the user
prompt manually for
now. So how can I
get my system specs?
That's what the
question we asked
before was. And I'm
just passing it in
here. And then
we are just getting
a completion from
the LLM and then
logging it. So let's
see how
this works. I can
simply do node slide1
index.mjs. Yeah, and
it, of course, gives
us the command
here in the content
file, content
property, which we
can use. And sorry,
I missed the
most important part,
which is the ES
modules bit. So
basically, in ES
modules, you can
import any types
from a TypeScript
file. So in this
case, you have to
import a TypeScript
file as an alias.
You have to do
something funky. You
have to do a type
def, then use
an import. So I'm
using import openai.openai.chatcompletion
message param, aliasing
it to chat message,
and
then using it to add
type safety to the
messages area here.
And I mean, I can
quickly show
you how it autocompletes.
So it autocompletes
to basically all of
the parameters being
imported
from openai. So in
this way, you can
add type safety to
your ESM component
without having
to do extra bits.
And since we are
using imports and
not requires, it
also automatically
imports
the types here. So
if you are using an
ESM import, then it
should automatically
import
the types without
having to explicitly
do that. But in this
case, of course, I'm
explicitly
typing this because
I want to ensure
that the messages
array here has the
type safety.
And of course, if
you try to add new
things, then it
tries to autocomplete
it for you.
So you can add a new
role with a specific
role name and stuff
like that. So yeah,
that's
the main benefit of
ESM and why I chose
to go with that, to
avoid a build step.
So the next problem
is that, yeah, oops,
I'm going, this is
going away too fast.
So yeah,
how do I add the
terminal bits? So
you have your simple
application right
now with just,
you know, it's a
node script, right?
It's not doing
anything special. It's
not exactly
a CLI tool. So how
do you add the
terminal bits like
reading from the
command line or
reading user input
and stuff like that?
So for doing that,
you use certain
tools, certain
libraries, just like
the JavaScript
ecosystem,
everything is a
library, npm install
away.
So there's commander
and inquirer, two
tools which you can
use. Commander is
used for creating
a nice CLI
experience around
your app. So you can
do things like
create new commands,
you can basically
add new commands,
accept certain
parameters, make
certain parameters
optional, stuff like
that. And inquirer
allows you to build
a nice user
interface, like a
prompt interface and
stuff like that,
which I had done
initially at the
start here with
my own tool. So in
this case, let's
have a look at how
it actually works.
So we'll only
look at commander
for now. To
initialize a new CLI
using commander, you
firstly import
command from
commander, which is
its base class, you
initialize it, and
then you can
pass it all of the
attributes that you
need to pass in here.
So in here, I'm
passing the
version of the CLI
tool and its
description. But if
you integrate it
into your product,
so it would look
something like this,
where you are using
program.argument. So
this is
the syntax for
adding a new sort of
command to your tool.
So you can add an
argument,
which is a query,
you add a
description to that
query, and then you
add in an action
which happens when
that query gets
passed in. So if
someone misses a
query, it
automatically
also does input
handling for you, so
it's sort of like XOR
for your CLI. And I'll
give
a quick demo of how
this works as well.
So we can do
something like node
cli2/final.mjs.
In this case, I am
taking the query
from the CLI, though,
so let's see what
happens if
I don't pass in the
query. I think it
should not, it will
still not fail in
this case because
an empty string will
be passed, but there's
only one way to find
out. So okay, yeah,
it
actually errors out.
So it does input
validation for us,
mainly it allows us
to avoid passing
in the wrong query,
and I think the help
command should work
as well. Yeah, so if
you run the
help command, then
it prints out all of
the things that you
had passed in in the
program.
So commander allows,
I mean, it just, it's
just a nice
experience to work
with while
building a new CLI.
And yeah, so how
would this actually
work if I manually
pass in a
command here? So I
can ask something
like list files in
current directory,
maybe. I
mean, of course, we
all know it's LS,
but we want to make
sure that our tool
is actually
working. So yeah, in
this case, it
returns LS. I don't
know what the extra
stuff being
passed in there is,
but it's mainly
because our prompt
is quite simple
right now, but
we can fix that
later. So right now,
yeah, we've got a
CLI tool, it accepts
a parameter
and based on that,
it's giving some
form of output. But
there's certain
things missing
here, of course. So
yeah, let's try to
deploy this. This is
something, this is
just a node
script right now,
right? We haven't
yet installed this
to our computer
using npm yet. So
let's
try to do that and
see what happens. So
what I can do is,
yeah, in this case,
in index.js
in slide three here,
it's the same file
that we were seeing
previously. I will
try to install
that now. So it's
actually very simple.
So to convert an npm
package into a CLI
is very
simple. You just add
a bin property to
your package.json,
and then you add the
name of
the command that you
want to use, and
then you add an
entry file for that.
So in this
case, the command I
want to use is how,
and the entry I want
to use is maybe
slide3/index.mjs.
And then, yeah, let's
try to install this
globally. So if I do
npm in -j, I think
that
was before. Yeah, I
just need to sudo
that, and then add
my password in. So
now if I try
to run how do I
maybe list my files,
then, okay, we are
actually getting a
really random
error, which is the
third problem that
we are facing, that,
yeah, this is being
treated
as bash. So as you
can see here, the
CLI itself, while
trying to run that
binary, is trying
to run the
JavaScript file as a
bash file, or like a
shell script file.
And so it returns
a random image magic
error in this case.
So how do we make it
treat JavaScript
files as
JavaScript files
while running them
from the CLI rather
than, you know,
trying to parse
it via bash or zsh
or whatever. So the
solution is to add a
shabang. So the shabang
that we
add here is
basically a shabang
user binenv node, so
it uses the user's
node environment
to run that specific
file. And this is a
very simple solution,
so it just adds a
new line
in the line up there,
and now it should
run for us. So to
quickly test this
out, sorry,
do you want me to go
there? Okay. Cool.
So, yeah, to quickly
test this out, we
can npm
install that again.
And now if we run
the how command,
then this time it
works, because
your command line
emulator, I guess
command line
emulator knows how
to treat that file.
So it knows to treat
that file as a node.js
file, and that's why
it's able to work
fine
this time. I'm sure
that I used the
wrong terminology
there, and someone
will correct
me later. And
problem four, so how
to make this crossOS
compatible. So right
now you
saw that we are
injecting into the
prompt that it has
to be, like it has
to return data
in zsh and for a Mac
OS device, but we
can, for example,
use something else.
Like, for
example, I might
want to use a
Windows laptop and
PowerShell or a
bash
as well, because
that's possible,
right? So the way
you would do that is
read the user's
environment. In
JavaScript, it's
super simple to do
that. You can use
process.env.shell,
which allows you to
import the user's
current execution
environment, so that
might be PowerShell
or bash scripts or
whatever. And then
you can get their
operating system
from platform
here. So if I
highlight on
platform, it shows a
list of all of the
possible values here.
And if I highlight
on shell, I think
shell itself is a
string, because
there are a lot
of environments out
there. And
interestingly enough,
this is super useful
if you're trying
to execute custom
code in a user's
environment. So in
my case, since I'm
executing commands,
I want to use the
right tool. I want
to use zsh or bash
or whatever the user
is executing
the command from,
and not any other
random tool which
might not be present
on the user's
operating system. So
if we modify the
command using that,
then we simply
inject those
variables
here. So after
importing shell, we
can just import
shell. So we say you're
an AI system
that only responds
with shell command
line instructions
for the OS platform.
And then
using that, our
prompt then is
automatically
customized to
whatever operating
system and
shell environment
that the user is
running the prompt
in. So of course, I'm
not going
to run this one
again, because it's
quite
straightforward. And
yeah, finally, so
relative
imports are sort of
bought. And this is
a problem which isn't
exactly unique to
CLI tools. It's
unique to anything
which is installed
in your node modules,
but wants to access
a file which
might be present in
a relative path-- I
guess, relative to
the node module
itself. So I'll
explain how. So the
ideal solution to
this would be to use
some path magic. So
you would
be able to use
underscore
underscore dirname
and stuff like that
to get the current
directory
that the file is
being currently
called from. And in
this case, I'll show
you why it might
not work in ES
modules. So for ES
modules-- so firstly,
let's try to use
relative imports
directly. For
example, if I want
to-- instead of
having to read the
data twice, so
instead
of having to write
what the user's
version was and what
the description of
the package
is twice, once in
the index.mjs file
here and once in
package.json, I can
deduplicate
it by reading it
from package.json
directly. So you
might think that you
can use import
package from package.json
directly, but ES
modules kind of
makes it difficult,
but that's
beyond the scope of
this talk. Another
solution you might
think of is using
JSON.parse and
then using read file
sync. So that's what
we're going to try
to do right now, and
then
I'll explain why
that might not work.
So once we do that,
let's try to install
it first.
So yeah, I go to
package.json again,
and then I do slide5/index.mjs,
and then I can do
sudo
npm install.globally.
And then if I try to
run how, then it
should throw me an
error.
Oh, it actually
works. I think that's
because I'm
executing from the
context of the root
directory, which
already has a
package.json here.
So relative to my
current path, I do
have a package.json.
But if I was in a
different file, so
if I went directly
up, and if I tried
to run that command
again, I think it
should throw the
error now. So yes,
now in this case
it says that no
search file or
directory, open
package.json,
because as you can
see here,
it's trying to read
it from relative to
the current path. So
again, if you've
worked with
Node.js in the past,
you would assume
that something like
underscore
underscore dirname
would work. So let's
try to do that. So I
would do something
like underscore
underscore
dirname, which
actually returns the
current directory
name when you are
using proper Node.js
without ES modules,
I guess. And if I
try to install this
now, I'll have to cd
into
the directory again,
and then npm install
this, go up a
directory again, and
try to--
oops, sorry. Run
that command. So in
this case, yeah, it
says dirname is not
defined
in ES module scope.
So we are sort of
shooting ourselves
in the foot here by
using ES modules
a little bit,
because a lot of the
things that you just
took for granted in
Node.js
are no longer
present. So the
solution for this is
actually using
import.meta.url
instead.
So I like to think
that ES modules
treat every file you're
using, like a
browser JavaScript
file. So in that
case, every file
itself has a URL. In
this case, the URL
for the file
would be the file
path, which points
to that particular
file. And you can
use the path
library from Node.js
itself to convert
that URL path into
file path. So file
URI to path,
and then you can
convert that into a
directory name
instead. And if you
use that, then it
works correctly this
time. And I've used
the double dots here,
because we want to
go one
directory up from
this directory. So
because the packet.json
file, of course,
exists in
the root directory,
not the slide five
directory. So if I
go back to package.json,
change this
to final.mjs, and
then npm install.
Yeah, I need to go
here, npm install.
And then if
I try to run the how
command by going up,
yeah, this time it
works fine, even
though
it's in a different
directory, because
it can just read
from the relative
path which
we have generated
there. So yeah, I
think that was
pretty much my talk,
so thank you.
I wanted to give a
very simple
introduction to how
to build CLIs, so
thanks. Yeah.
>> What are these
type definitions in
commands? >> Yeah,
so sorry for not
explaining it well.
Those are basically
JS docs type
definitions. So
instead of having to
use TypeScript type
definitions, which
you would use if you
were using TypeScript,
you can now use JS
doc type
definitions, which
support all of TypeScript's
type definitions as
well. So instead of
having
to use a build tool
to convert TypeScript
files into
JavaScript files,
you can now use
JavaScript
files directly with
JS docs comments
inside of them,
which define the
types of the
variables
that you want to use.
>> Yeah, but is it
just the dot, is it
just
the quotation? >>
Yeah, yeah, it
actually checks the
types.
So you can use TSC
to type check JS doc
comments as well.
>> Okay, but then
you use TSC, so if
you don't use TSC.
>> Yeah, you don't
get type checks, but
you don't need to
use a build tool, so
that's
the main advantage.
>> Yes, so you, okay,
so you don't use TSC,
so we didn't check
the types, you just
identified, but you
could check them
with TSC beyond.
>> Yeah, yeah,
exactly. >> It's
brilliant.
>> Thanks. >> Thank
you so much.
>> Yeah, no worries.
>> A couple of
questions, actually.
>> Yeah. >> You know
when you moved one
directory outside
of where the problem
was installed, right?
If you run a command,
it works. Now if you
moved two
directories outside,
it'll work. >> Yeah,
of course. You can
navigate anywhere,
and it will still
work, because, I
mean, I'll explain
the reason why it
will still work,
and then I'll show
you how it works. So
the reason why it
would work is that
we are, sorry,
or git blame is
picking up there. So
yeah, import.meta.urls
points to this
specific file,
and whatever context
this file is running
in, be it like an NPM
module or locally
via
Node.js script or
whatever, this value
will always point to
wherever this file
is located,
and so we are
converting that file
path URI to a path
instead, which is
then allowing
us to do this, which
points to the actual
package.json file.
And now I can, yeah,
so
I can go anywhere,
and I'll still, if I
run the how command,
it will still point
to the
right file there. >>
Yeah, that makes
sense.
>> One of the
questions is, Node.js
should ban? >> Yeah.
>> I assume they don't
have Node.js on your
system. >> Yeah.
>> All right, how
does that help you?
>> Yeah, so in that
case, it will
definitely
be a problem. So
this package, having
a package.json and
installing a library
using NPM install
assumes that you
have got Node.js
already installed in
your machine, so
that's a big
assumption that we
are making here. Of
course, we would use
something like Golang
if we wanted
to, you know, make
it independent of
having Node.js
installed, I guess.
Yeah. >> [INAUDIBLE]
>> So it should be
able to do that, so
I can ask it, for
example, well, let's
install my
actual tool, so,
yeah, if I do that,
it should install it
globally, and now I
can do something
like if I go to the
directory first, how
do I create a Python
server file and save
it
locally maybe, so
that it knows that I
actually want to
save that as well.
Then, I mean, again,
this isn't something
that my tool is
doing, that this is
something that the GPT
API is
returning, of course.
So if it returns
this command, let's
try to execute it.
So it hasn't
returned anything
yet, but, yeah, we
see server.py, so it
created server.py
here somewhere, yeah.
So it created some
output and then pasted
it to server.py, so
if I do cat server.py,
then yeah, it still
has that, because
you can do it by
Unix commands, right?
So as long
as you can do it by
Unix commands or
PowerShell commands
or whatever, the CLI
tool should
be able to help you
with that. Yeah. Any
other questions? No?
Okay. Yeah. Oh,
sorry. Go on.
It's actually very
cheap. So GPT 4.0
mini, I think it's
the cheapest tool
out there.
It costs like 0.005
dollars per token or
something. I mean,
of course, people
can correct me if
I'm wrong, but I
think it's like
super cheap. I have
put in $10 in, I
would say, like very
early this year,
maybe February or
something, but I
haven't still run
out just by building
this tool and
working on other
side projects. Okay.
Okay. Yeah, yeah, so
it's super cheap.
But I think the GPT
4.0 mini performs
really bad as
compared to GPT 4.0,
especially if
you're trying to do
stuff like run
commands
successfully on your
command line, I
think.
Yeah, yeah, it's
definitely faster.
Make sense? Yeah. So
yeah, that's my
website. Reach out
to me if you want to.
And I'm available
for independent
consulting on any AI
projects
you might have. So
thank you.
I'm just waiting for
you.